Guide to the Trinity College Library records, 1892-1924
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Trinity College Library records 1892-1924
University Archives, Duke University
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Library.
5.2 Linear Feet 2,250 Items
In 1887 the Trinity College Library was created when two rival literary societies combined their book collections and added them to the few books already owned by the school.
Records kept by the librarians and staff of the Trinity College Library documenting its operations. Included are records of accessions, book orders, circulation, periodicals, and reference books. The records also contain a short history of the Library by Joseph Penn Breedlove as well as the brochure for the opening of the new library building in 1903.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Trinity College Library records were received by the University Archives as transfers over a period of time.
Historical Note
In 1887 the Trinity College Library was created when two rival literary societies combined their book collections and added them to the few books already owned by the school. The Columbian Society, founded in 1846, and the Hesperian Society, founded in 1851, maintained libraries for their members and competed in acquiring books. According to the Trinity College Catalogue, by 1860 each society held 2,200 volumes, while the school itself held only 650. In 1887, new president John Franklin Crowell persuaded the literary societies to merge their collections with that of the college, creating a combined library of 10,000 volumes. The new library was housed on the second floor of the old Trinity College chapel, and Crowell claimed to have catalogued each of the books himself.
After Trinity moved to Durham in 1892, the library occupied a large single room in the Washington Duke Building, the main building of the campus. One student from each of the two literary societies served as librarians. The Washington Duke Building burned in 1911, but by that time, the library had moved to a new location.
In 1900, James B. Duke donated money to create a separate free standing library building. Ground was broken in 1901, and the Trinity College Library building was completed in December, 1902, with a formal opening taking place the following February. During construction, Duke donated an additional $10,000 for the purchase of books.
After the creation of the Duke Endowment in December 1924, a new building was constructed, seventy-five yards northwest from the old library, to serve as the library for the university during the construction of West Campus and the transformation of Trinity College into Duke University. After the new library was completed 1927, 100,000 books were moved from the old to the new library, a feat that was accomplished by arranging a competition among fraternities to see which could move the most books.
The expansion plans for East Campus called for the demolition of the old library. It was dismantled, moved to Kittrell College in Kittrell, North Carolina, and rebuilt as the B. N. Duke Library. It remained there, looking almost exactly the same as it had at Trinity, until 1972 when it was destroyed by fire.
Collection Overview
Records kept by the librarians and staff of the Trinity College Library documenting its operations. Included are records of accessions, book orders, circulation, periodicals, and reference books. The records also contain a short history of the Library by Joseph Penn Breedlove as well as the brochure for the opening of the new library building in 1903.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Acquisitions (Libraries)
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Library
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, receipts, and miscellaneous administrative records, 1893-1923 (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, receipts, and miscellaneous administrative records, 1923-1924 (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, receipts, and miscellaneous administrative records, 1924 and undated (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - History of the Trinity College Library from late 1890s when it was located in the Washington Duke Building
  - Library history clippings and related materials
  - Trinity College Library Association brochure, 1899
  - Trinity College Library opening, 1903
  - Book requests, 1907-1924 (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Periodical records, 1901-1903
  - Periodical and book records, 1913-1922
  - Library order books, 1901-1906 (2 volumes) (Box 5)
  - Acquisitions, 1902-1903 (2 volumes)
  - Acquisitions, 1919-1924
  - Books, periodicals bought by departments, 1923-1924 (2 folders)
  - Circulation records, 1892, 1895-1902 (10 volumes) (Box 6)
  - Circulation record, Ethel Carr Peacock reading room, 1897-1899
  - Law, circulation record, 1912-1919 (Box 7)
  - Fines, 1900
  - Biology Reference Shelf, 1910-1923
  - Economics Reference Shelf, 1910-1924
  - English Literature Reference Shelf, 1909-1924
  - Trinity College Library, Records of Books, 1909-1923 (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - Trinity College Library, Record of Expenditures, 1911-1912
  - Trinity College Library, Record of Philosophy Shelf, 1910-1924
  - Trinity College Library, Record of Books put on New Book Shelf, 1909-1919
  - Trinity College Library, Record of Mordecai's law lectures and McIntosh's select cases on contracts, 1908-1911
  - Trinity Park School, Record of Reference Shelf, 1909-1922